Today's דף Daf *daf* is יא *Yod Aleph*, it's also 11 days
in the עומר *Omer* and also I haven't don't realize don't understand
why I didn't realize this it's 11 days in April. Anyway all
the planets are aligned it must be very significant.
Anyway what can happen when it's the 49th day of April? Okay
anyway so then so we pick up on the bottom of יא
עמוד ב *Yod Aleph Amud Bet* we're in the middle of a
nice section of אגדתא Agadata *Agadata* from what I understand you left
up you left off with where ואמר עולא Ulla תמר Tamar. זינתה
*Ve'amar Ulla Tamar Zinta*. Okay right so it's right under there's a
vav in parentheses about 11 lines from the bottom. Okay and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is dealing with you know it started with
a דרשה drasha *drasha* about אשר נשיא Nasi יחטא אשרי נשיא Nasi
*asher nasi yecheta ashrei nasi* praised is the king who's able to
publicly accept the fact that he has sinned and brings a קרבן
korban *korban* and that's sort of a model for the
generation and then left led out to a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* about
יש הבל *yesh hevel* speaking about the מעשה צדיקים tzaddikim *ma'aseh tzadikim*
and the מעשה רשעים *ma'aseh resha'im* and what and you know the
rewards that they get or the punishments that they get in this
world and then comparing you know that צדיקים ילכו בם ופושעים יכשלו
בם *tzadikim yelchu bam uposhim yichashlu bam* same type of an act
could be a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* for some and an עבירה aveirah
*aveirah* for others and that has then led you know the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* to discuss about this issue about like right about לוט
Lot *Lot* and about an act that for maybe the daughters was
a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* and for לוט Lot *Lot* was an עבירה
aveirah, *aveirah*. Okay so that's very interesting about how intent or you
know can maybe completely change the character of the act. Okay so
with that in mind we're going to continue and it says the
following ואמר עולא תמר Tamar זינתה וזמרי זינה *Ve'amar Ulla Tamar zinta
veZimri zina*. So תמר Tamar *Tamar* fornicated and זמרי *Zimri* fornicated. Okay
תמר *Tamar* Zimri was the one who was with you know the
by there by the whole story with פנחס *Pinchas*. Okay so תמר
זינתה יצאו ממנה מלכים ונביאים *Tamar zinta yatzu mimena melachim unevi'im*. So
תמר *Tamar* fornicated and from and she merited that you know she
had a child from יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* eventually from there descended מלכות
בית דוד malchus Beis David. *Malchus Beis David* etc. so from her
came kings and prophets because her intent was לשם שמים leshem shamayim
*leshem shamayim* and זמרי זינה *veZimri zina* and זמרי *Zimri* fornicated and
his intent was completely you know either his lust or maybe even
worse as a way of like sort of you know a protest
against God and ונפלו כמה רבבות מישראל *venafelu kama rivavos miYisrael* and
look how many thousands died as a result. אמר רב נחמן Rav
Nachman: בר יצחק גדולה עבירה לשמה aveirah lishmah ממצוה שלא לשמה shelo
lishmah *Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak gedola aveirah lishma mimitzvah shelo lishma*.
Great is this is a very sort of powerful and potentially dangerous
line of גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* great is an עבירה aveira. *aveirah* done
for the right intention greater than a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* done for
the wrong intention שנאמר she'ne'emar, *shene'emar* as it says תבורך מנשים minashim,
יעל אשת חבר הקיני מנשים באוהל תבורך *Tevorach minashim Yael eshes Chever
HaKeini minashim baohel
tevorach* blessed from women should יעל *Yael* be blessed the wife of
חבר הקיני *Chever HaKeini* מנשים באוהל תבורך *minashim baohel tevorach* more than
women in the tent she should be blessed. מני אינון נשים באוהל
*Mani inun nashim baohel* who are the women in the tent? שרה
רבקה רחל ולאה *Sarah Rivka Rachel v'Leah*. So those are you know
the אמהות *Imahot* איה שרה אשתך ויאמר הנה באוהל *ayeh Sarah ishtecha
vayomer hineh baohel*. So therefore now why are they considered to do
a מצוה שלא לשמה mitzvah shelo lishmah, *mitzvah shelo lishma*? So the
תוספות ראש Rosh *Tosafot Rosh* says well since the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
doesn't say any otherwise we assume like any husband and wife part
of the reason that they're having you know sex has to do
with the fact that they have a physical attraction for one another
there's sexual desire. So it's not necessarily a bad thing it's a
natural thing but there's an element of personal satisfaction in it as
opposed to the case of יעל *Yael* when she had sex with
סיסרא *Sisra* which is not explicit in the verse but it is
heavily you know חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* are not making it up it
is like the heavy subtext of the whole you know of the
שירת דבורה *Shiras Devorah* and so on about this point. Anyway
nevertheless so you know so there she was she was a married
woman and she was sleeping with another man but nevertheless she was
doing it out of absolutely no sense of personal pleasure or you
know or or you know sort of self-interest it was all done
for the לשם שמים l'shem shamayim? *leshem shamayim*. Okay next one minute
let's finish this point. Okay אימא eima, *eima* so the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says so you see that she's even more blessed than שרה
רבקה רחל ולאה *Sarah Rivka Rachel v'Leah*. איני *Eini* is this really
true? והאמר רב יהודה Yehuda אמר רב לעולם יעסוק אדם בתורה ובמצות
אפילו שלא לשמה shelo lishmah שמתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה Shemitoch shelo
lishma ba lishma, *Veha'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav le'olam ya'asok adam baTorah
u'vemitzos afilu shelo lishma shemitoch shelo lishma ba lishma* you should always
involve yourself in תורה Torah *Torah* and מצות *mitzvos* even for the
less than ideal reason not you know not necessarily out of pure
motivations because out of less than pure motivations you'll wind up doing
it out of pure motivations and I don't exactly understand what the
point is. It doesn't say it's as good as לשמה lishmah, *lishma*
it recognizes that it's not as good it just says it's a
you know it's a positive thing to be doing it but maybe
what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* feels is is that since in one
case you have somebody actually doing a מצוה *mitzvah* and even though
they're doing it שלא לשמה shelo lishma. *shelo lishma* we don't sort
of say that that's a negative thing.
How could you say that an עבירה לשמה aveirah lishmah, is weightier
than that? If שלא לשמה shelo lishma? was a clear negative, was
a clear bad thing, then I can get saying that עבירה לשמה
aveirah lishma is better. But if שלא לשמה shelo lishma. is an
acceptable thing and a positive thing, you should be doing it, I
mean ideally לשמה, lishma but even if לא לשמה, lo lishmah, you
should, then how can you say an עבירה aveira could ever be
better? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, ela, so fine, so the
גמרא Gemara modifies it, you know,
moderates it a little bit. So where were we? אימא,
אימא כי מצוה שלא לשמה. eima ki mitzvah shelo lishmah. So it's
not that it's better than a מצוה שלא לשמה, mitzvah shelo lishmah.
it's equal to a מצוה שלא לשמה. mitzvah shelo lishma, So נשים
באוהל מנשים nashim baohel minashim somehow is not meaning greater than the
women in the tent, but from among the women in the tent.
She's as blessed as Sarah, Rebecca, Rachel, and Leah.
Or would be blessed like מנשים, like from women in the tent,
Sarah, Rebecca, Rachel, and Leah would love to give something like that,
they're blessed.
Could be. Okay, anyway, bottom line is is that this is of
course a very, you know, to use a scholarly phrase, an antinomian
גמרא, Gemara a very dangerous גמרא, Gemara. because, you know, the entire—
what does antinomian actually mean? Nomos is law. Okay, it goes against
the system of law. You know, it's all about that your heart
is in the right place, it doesn't really matter what you're doing
as long as your heart is in the right place, you know,
and it can obviously justify terrible things, doing עבירה שלא לשמה, aveirah
shelo lishmah, you know, it's even, I mean excuse me, עבירה aveira.
לשמה, lishma? you know, as long as you're doing עבירות aveiros and
you're doing it for the right reason, it's even as good or
you know as מצוות, mitzvos, you know, and like you know the
whole sort of Frank, the Frankists, you know, the sort of the
descendants of שבתאי צבי, Shabbetai Tzvi, you know, were very much sort
of about the about the— I mean although that also was about
doing עבירות aveiros to bring the משיח Moshiach because the משיח Moshiach
only comes in a generation that's all זכאי או חייב, zakai o
chayav, so it's much easier to get to all חייב chayav than
all זכאי. zakai. So anyway, but like doing, you know, anyway, the
idea of doing עבירות לשמה, aveiros lishmah, you know, and giving license
to that is of course, you know, very dangerous. Some of this
does though does play out in Chassidic literature, you know, in acknowledging
the power of, you know, doing things with the right intention, and
sometimes, you know, there are a small number of cases where we
do say— I mean so much of הלכה, halacha, the point of
הלכה halacha is against the thinking that the ends justify the means.
Right, הלכה halacha is all about, you know what, I really don't
care what your what what goal you're trying to accomplish, like, you
know, it all matters about the rightness of the particular act and
that has to be acceptable. You know, there are times where some
things outweigh other things, like you know פקוח נפש pikuach nefesh outweighs
שבת, Shabbat, but that's because— but that's keeping within the framework that
הלכה halacha has set up and that's still saying that the rightness
of the act is because it's an act of saving a life.
Okay, and it's defined as an act of saving a life and
not like, you know, whereas obviously to say that well we're all
doing it for the greater good and it's all ultimately to serve
לשם l'shem שמים can give license to a lot of terrible things.
So it is interesting, you know, that the גמרא, Gemara on the
other hand, you know, there are rare times where you have people
have to do acts that are not licensed by law and ultimately
it's the right thing to do because of the circumstances.
There was one of the Chassidic masters said
today the Christians worship שקר sheker but with אמת, emes, and we
worship אמת emes but with שקר. sheker. It plays very much into
this.
I'm going to have to figure— we'll have to talk about that
more later, I can't fully understand or unpack that one right now.
But anyway, but I but you know, there are some time cases
where you know where ultimately somebody just, you know, where where you
have to do the right thing even if there's like, but it's
dangerous, it's dangerous to put it out there and it can obviously
be very significantly abused. So I don't have an answer to that,
but I just want to put it out that this is a
line that does runs deeply against the entire halachic system, and and
it's and it's an idea that can be very, very dangerous and
justify a lot of horrific things if it's misused. But it doesn't
mean that there are not times where actually you have to save
כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael from this evil general or whatever, you know,
there's no, you know, now maybe you could say why isn't that
a הלכה halacha of פקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, you know, why isn't
that, you know, some type of a thing? Well, but it's עריות,
arayos, עריות arayos doesn't justify פקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, you know, it's
supposed to be יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg ve'al ya'avor even for עריות
arayos or whatever, you know, but like, so okay, but does that
mean that that sometimes there aren't exceptional cases that can't be contained
within a legal system? Because you know legal system can't anticipate all
the realities of the world and all the high exceptional cases where
it's completely, you know, where the circumstances obviously justify it. But, you
know, but then you have to but whatever, but you know, but
you have to accept that those are the rare rare exceptions.
Yeah, just to pick up on what you just said, I was
just thinking of אסתר ואחשורוש, Esther veAchashverosh, right, you know, and then
the other thing was that—
right, though the גמרא Gemara tries to make אסתר ואחשורוש Esther veAchashverosh
work within its sort of system, you know, אסתר קרקע עולם Esther
karka olam and so on, yeah.
But but to pick up, you know, I just find it very
interesting about the flow of the גמרא Gemara we just talked about.
about sex and לוט Lot and the רשע rasha and then צדיקים
בנות לוט. Bnot Lot. But what's interesting is then we just talk
about יהודה Yehuda and תמר. Well, יהודה Yehuda was
לשם זנות, l'shem zenut, תמר was לשם whatever it is, מצוה. But
we didn't use יהודה Yehudah, and תמר as that example. We don't
want to call יהודה as a רשע. rasha. But it's really very,
I mean, it's a very good point. And it is mentioned right
after the other.
Or not,
you're right, maybe it
isn't. Yeah, well right because it's from the union of the two.
Practical application today, Mossad agents sleeping with their targets to get intelligence
or even better.
I mean that
happens, they do that. Right.
The way I see it, it's not that it's encouraging עבירה, it's
discouraging apathy. That apathy is the worst thing.
Well, especially comparing לשמה lishma, to שלא לשמה.
shelo lishma, It could be the הוה אמינא hava amina here, which
I
diametrically oppose than someone that just doesn't give a...
Well that was Rav Kook's line. Rav Kook basically said
that
at least something
exactly something
about like the, yeah he also like, atheists at least had a
passion. They were at least like rejecting the false god of their
youth, but they were looking for the truth. So it was like,
anyway, but exactly that, somebody that rather than being apathetic. So I
think obviously there's a lot of that here. I just want to
point out that that doesn't mean that this cannot be potentially dangerous
and misused, but I appreciate your point. Okay, let's continue.
Yeah exactly, maybe they were afraid to teach it to you in
ישיבה. yeshiva. Okay. So anyway, but I like the point that you're
starting, it's really about being passionate and not just doing things out
of rote and apathy. But again, but still, all right,
it's potentially dangerous. Okay, so anyway, moving on. איהי דבישראל, Ai hi
d'veYisrael, we just did that. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, שבע
בעילות בעל אותו רשע באותה שעה, Sheva be'ilot ba'al oto rasha b'ota
sha'ah,
seven acts of intercourse that ססירא Sisera did at that moment, שנאמר,
as it says, בין רגליה כרע נפל בין רגליה כרע נפל באשר
כרע שם נפל
שדוד. Bein ragleha kara nafal bein ragleha kara nafal ba'asher kara sham
nafal shadud. Anyway, if you count all the times that talks about
verbs bowing down and falling etc., it's seven. Anyway, this פסוק pasuk
is obviously, even Bible scholars say obviously it's suggesting the act of
intercourse, it's not just חז"ל Chazal making this up. והא קא מתהני
מעבירה, V'ha ka mit'hani me'aveirah,
now what do you mean that it was
שלא לשמה? lishma, Even if I keep saying that wrong, what do
you mean that it was לשמה? lishma. What do you mean that
she was doing it לשם שמים? Maybe that was motivating her, but
it wasn't a completely pure act, she was getting pleasure out of
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, all right, so she wasn't forced,
right, she was seducing him. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן
יוחי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, אפילו טובתם של
רשעים רעה היא אצל צדיקים. Afilu tovatan shel resha'im ra'ah hi eitzel
tzaddikim. No, she still even something that the good that you get
from the wicked is considered evil and disgusting when the righteous
receive, get something that even if it would be conceived of otherwise
to be considered something pleasurable or good. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, לעולם יעסוק אדם בתורה ובמצוות אפילו שלא
לשמה, Le'olam ya'asok adam b'Torah u'vmitzvot afilu shelo lishma, going back to
that line. Okay, now that we've praised the value of לשמה, that
even an עבירה לשמה is better than a מצוה שלא לשמה, nevertheless
or as good as, nevertheless it shouldn't mean like why bother שלא
לשמה. No, no, let's not forget about the power of the act
in itself, even if the motivation is not there. Do the act
even for not the right reason, שמתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה, because
that will ultimately lead hopefully to for the right reason. It doesn't
always work that way. Right, a lot of people just get brought
up on what the פוסקים poskim call מצוות אנשים מלומדה, mitzvot anashim
melumada, like just doing מצוות mitzvot out of rote and it never
leads to לשמה, it just leads to, maybe habituating practice and there's
a benefit of a life of ritual or a life of practice
and observance, but it doesn't always lead to לשמה. Okay. Anyway,
you might שבשכר מצוה, she'bischar mitzvah, now but here's the example, שבשכר
מ"ב קרבנות שהקריב בלק הרשע. She'bischar arbaim u'shtayim korbanot she'hikriv Balak harasha.
So that's תורה ומצוות?
Torah u'vmitzvot? מ"ב קרבנות. Arbaim u'shtayim korbanot. Yeah, well they're קרבנות. korbanot.
They're being brought... לעבודה זרה? l'avodah zarah? No, he's understanding it that
it's brought for God, since בלעם Bilaam recognized God and he says
bring me these
קרבנות korbanot and he's going to God to get his inspiration or
whatever, he understands, all right, anyway, he understands that these קרבנות korbanot
were brought to God and this is worse than a normal שלא
לשמה, this is for an evil purpose, this is to curse Israel.
שבשכר מ"ב קרבנות שהקריב בלק הרשע, She'bischar arbaim u'shtayim korbanot she'hikriv Balak
harasha, for the merit of those 42,
זכה ויצאה ממנו רות. zachah ve'yatzah mimenu Ruth. Ultimately from him came
רות, Ruth, who was from מואב Moav and understood by חז"ל to
be a descendant of בלק. Balak. Then as רש"י Rashi says, and
from רות Ruth came דוד, David, and דוד David sang and praised
to God, which is sort of similar to the
קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. Significance? We can't ask too many questions, we got
a lot of
גמרא. Gemara דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, De'amar Rabbi Yosi bar Rabbi
Chanina, רות בת בנו של עגלון בן בנו של בלק מלך מואב.
Ruth bat bno shel Eglon ben bno shel Balak melech Moav. Okay.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, מניין שאין הקדוש ברוך הוא מקפח אפילו שכר
שיחה נאה, minayin she'ein HaKadosh Baruch Hu mikapei'ach afilu sechar sichah na'ah,
where do you know that God does not withhold from people even
the reward for even like just a few nice words? God rewards
us for everything we do.
מהכא, Meihacha, דאילו בכירה דקריא... de'ilu bechirah d'karya... The older daughter back
to לוט who called her son מואב, Moav, which is a little
explicit, from the father, so it’s a little blunt, so when he
came to not fighting them, God said to משה, Moshe, אל תצר
את מואב ואל תתגר בם מלחמה, al tatzar et Moav ve-al tityar
bam milchama, do not oppress them and do not sort of provoke
war. So the גמרא Gemara says, מלחמה הוא דלא, milchama hu delo,
so we can’t provoke war, הא ציורי צרינהו, ha tziyurei tzareinhu, you
can actually do things to cause them to cause them a little
bit of anguish and suffering. I don’t know how that works with
אל תצר, al tatzar, it’s like ציורי tziyurei and אל תצר. al
tatzar. But anyway, somehow it’s read like you can do certain things
to them. ואילו צעירה דקריא בן עמי, ve-ilu tze'irah de-karya Ben-Ami, the
younger daughter who called her son בן עמי, Ben-Ami, which is much
vague, the son of my nation, you know, עמון. Amon. So אמר
ליה, amar leih, God says, אל תצורם ואל תתגר בם, al tatzurem
ve-al tityar bam, do not provoke them כלל klal at all, אפילו
ציורי לא, afilu tziyurei lo, don’t even do anything to cause them
any anguish. אמר רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה,
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Avin amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, לעולם יקדים
אדם לדבר מצוה, le-olam yakdim adam li-devar mitzvah, you should always sort
of run to חאפ chap a מצוה. שבשכר, She-be-sechar, so this is
again dealing with sort of like passion and
motivation, שבשכר לילה אחת שקדמתה בכירה לצעירה, she-be-sechar layla achat she-kidmata bechira
li-tze'irah, for just having beat, you know, for the older daughter having
got one night in before the younger daughter, okay before we were
saying the older daughter did wrong by being so blunt, but at
least she was so put herself forward that she was the first
one to do this, she was also the initiator, okay, זכתה וקדמה
ארבע דורות למלכות. zachta ve-kidma arba dorot le-malchut. So her descendants
came ארבע דורות, arba dorot, four generations before
for kingdom. What does that mean? Because מואב, Moav, you know, רות
Rut is from מואב, Moav, and that’s דוד, David, and it took
four generations until you had somebody in the Jewish line that came
from עמון, Amon, which is who which is רחבעם Rechavam בן שלמה,
ben Shlomo, who was born from נעמה העמונית. Na'amah Ha-Ammonit. Okay, so
therefore so it was four generations prior within the מלכות malchut of
ישראל. Yisrael.
You believe this is a מצוה that these two girls?
Yeah, well that’s what we said before, שצדיקים ילכו בם. she-tzaddikim yelchu
bam. Okay, it was לוט that did it for an עבירה. Okay.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, מעם הארץ, Me-am ha-aretz, now we’re moving on
from the אגדתא and now back to the הלכה. Halacha. Okay, so
now we’re getting to the normal חטאת chatat that somebody brings if
they sin. And again remember that the משיח Mashiach and the נשיא
Nasi. do not bring a חטאת, chatat, they bring their own thing,
they bring I mean they bring a חטאת, chatat, but they bring
their own special קרבנות. korbanot. The משיח Mashiach for פסקנינג paskening and
then acting and he brings a פר, par, and the נשיא Nasi?
just for acting and he brings a שעיר. se'ir. But these are
the פסוקים pesukim about a כשבה kesbah or שעירה, se'irah, a she-goat
and a she-sheep or whatever ewe that are brought by a normal
person who does a sin. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, מעם הארץ, Me-am
ha-aretz, if somebody sins from among the people of the land, פרט
למשיח, prat le-Mashiach, that excludes the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. מעם הארץ,
Me-am ha-aretz, it also פרט לנשיא, prat le-Nasi, it excludes the נשיא.
Nasi, Now why do you have to exclude them?
ולאו כבר יצאו משיח בפר ונשיא בשעיר? Ve-lav kevar yatzu Mashiach be-par
ve-Nasi be-se'ir? We already know that they have their special קרבן korban
when they do their sins. שיכול, She-yachol, because I might have thought
משיח על העלם דבר שגגת מעשה מביא פר, Mashiach al he'elem davar
shegegat ma'aseh meivi par, על שגגת מעשה לחודיה מייתי כשבה ושעירה. al
shegegat ma'aseh le-chudeih meiti kesbah ve-se'irah. No, maybe I would have said
like this, when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has the special conditions,
the פסק psak and the action, that’s when he has his special
קרבן korban and he brings the cow, the ox. But when he
just sins by action like any normal individual, he brings the חטאת
chatat of a normal individual, the she-goat or the she-lamb. So תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, מעם הארץ, Me-am ha-aretz, פרט למשיח. prat le-Mashiach. No,
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is completely excluded from the normal קרבנות
korbanot of a חטאת, chatat, and by a normal sin by an
error by action he brings no sin offering, the only time he
brings is when he satisfies the conditions of the כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. He should be held to a higher standard, no? I understand.
Okay, מעם הארץ, Me-am ha-aretz, now that explains why we needed to
exclude a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, to say that he doesn’t bring
when it’s by his normal sins of actions, you know, a normal
חטאת. chatat. The only time he brings a חטאת chatat is when
it’s also with the פסק. psak. But now מעם הארץ, Me-am ha-aretz,
פרט לנשיא. prat le-Nasi. So now why do we have to exclude
the נשיא? Nasi תינח משיח, Tenach Mashiach, I understand why you have
to exclude the משיח. Mashiach. אלא נשיא בשגגת מעשה הוא דמייתי, Ela
Nasi be-shegegat ma'aseh hu de-meiti, the נשיא, Nasi right, which we’ll say
is the king, so the only conditions for him to bring his
special קרבן korban of the goat, of the שעיר, se'ir, is when
it’s a sin of action alone. So the תורה Torah, clearly already
assigns him a sin offering, the שעיר. se'ir. Why do I have
to then exclude him from the standard sin offering of a normal
person? He’s implicitly excluded, he’s given his own special קרבן korban. for
the same circumstances.
So אמר רב זביד משמיה דרבא, Amar Rav Zevid mishmei de-Rava, הכא
במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון שאכל
כזית חלב כשהוא הדיוט ונתמנה ואחר כך נודע לו. Kegon she-achal kezayit
chelev keshe-hu hedyot ve-nitmaneh ve-achar kach noda lo. Okay, so basically he
ate חלב chelev when he was a commoner and then he was
appointed as a king, and then he realized he ate חלב. chelev.
So therefore I might think that now he brings like a commoner.
So it says no, now that you’re a king, even though the
sin was when you were a commoner, you’re not going to bring
the חטאת chatat of a commoner. One minute. So סלקא דעתך אמינא
salka deitach amina I might think נשיא כשהוא עשירה nesi k'sheu ashira
קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that you don't, it's telling you
don't bring the חטאת chatas of a commoner even if you sinned
as a commoner if now you're a king. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute.
If he sinned as a king, then he would still bring the
regular חטאת. chatas.
No, no, no. Obviously if you sin as a king, you bring
your special קרבן. korban But even if you sin as a commoner,
don't bring your, you know, you don't bring a normal קרבן korban
because now you're a king.
No, a regular sin, not like if you followed the בית דין
Beis Din בהוראה.
behora'ah. No, no, no, no. A נשיא Nasi. only brings for שגגת
מעשה. shiggas ma'aseh. It does not need special conditions. That's exactly why
the גמרא Gemara doesn't know why you need a פסוק pasuk to
exclude him. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says הניחא לרבי שמעון, haniacha
l'Rabbi Shimon, that's good according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon דאזיל בתר
ידיעה d'azil basar yediyoh because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that it
also matters when you found out. That's exactly his פסק psak that
a נשיא Nasi, who sins as a commoner and finds out as
a king does not bring the חטאת chatas of a commoner because
it also goes by when you are, become aware of your sin.
אלא לרבנן דאזלי בתר חטאה, ela l'rabbanan d'azli basar chata'ah, but according
to the רבנן Rabbanan that go by the only the time of
sin, so they would say if you sinned as a commoner and
found out as a king, you bring the קרבן korban of a
commoner. So פסוק מאי למיהוי, pasuk mai l'meyhvei, so the פסוק pasuk.
can't be excluding that case because according to the רבנן Rabbanan you
actually do bring the חטאת chatas of a commoner in that case.
אלא אמר רב זביד משמיה דרבא, ela amar Rav Zvid mishmeih d'Rava,
so רב זביד Rav Zvid says in the name of רבא, Rava,
הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שאכל כזית חלב כשהוא הדיוט. hacha b'mai askinan
kegon she'achal kezayis chelev k'shehu hedyot. Fine, here's what the case is.
You're eating half of the כזית kezayis of חלב chelev as a
commoner, ונתמנה, venismaneh, and then somebody came and said, "Hey, you were
just appointed king." And you said, "Great, but let me just let
me finish my sandwich," okay, and you kept on chomping on it.
Of course you're שוגג, shogeg, you're not knowingly sinning, that's why we're
talking about a חטאת. chatas. והשלימו, vehishlimo, and you finished eating your
sandwich because it also has to be תוך כדי אכילת פרס, toch
k'dei achilas pras, okay, and now ואחר כך נודע לו, v'achar kach
noda lo, now you found out. So therefore half of the כזית
kezayis as a commoner and half as a king. So סלקא דעתך
אמינא salka deitach amina I might think that since the act started
as a commoner, we should see this as just the culmination of
the act and it should be judged as a sin you did
as a commoner,
נצטרף ונייתי כשהוא עשירה nitzataref v'neisei k'shehu ashira bring the קרבן korban,
of a commoner, קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. So that's why
the פסוק pasuk. has to say מעם הארץ m'am ha'aretz to exclude
a נשיא. Nasi, Even if you became a king in the middle
of your act, that is enough to exempt you, tell you that
you do not bring the normal חטאת chatas of a נשיא, Nasi
and therefore you don't bring any חטאת chatas for this act, because
you didn't sin as a נשיא, Nasi so you're not going to
bring that special קרבן, korban and you didn't sin fully as a
commoner, so it's going to be a type of an act that
you don't bring any קרבן korban for. For כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
there'll be lots of acts he doesn't bring any קרבן korban. for.
Anytime he does a normal sin בשוגג, b'shogeg, he's not going to
bring a קרבן. korban, He needs a פסוק. pasuk. But a נשיא
Nasi, doesn't need a פסוק. pasuk. So under normal cases, a נשיא
nasi will always bring either the שעיר sa'ir if he sinned as
a נשיא, nasi or the שעירה se'irah or the כשבה kisbah if
he sinned as a commoner, okay, because it's always the exact same
conditions. The only case we're excluding here that he brings nothing is
he did half and half. Yes.
So it's assuming here, presumably these are assumed, these are נשיאים nesi'im
who are מלכות בית דוד. Beit David, Right.
Well, we'll talk about that, but yeah. Okay.
But, so,
a member of that family is a הדיוט hedyot until the very
minute they become king.
Correct. That is correct. Yeah. I mean, that's a good point. It's
not like they come up to some total person who's like, "Huh?
What?" like, you know, right, they're going to a member of the
royal family. And nevertheless, there's a sense of נתמנה nismaneh which we'll
get to some of that in a minute.
Yeah. Okay. בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן. ba'i minei Rava meRav Nachman.
Now רבא Rava asked רב נחמן: נשיאות מהו שתפסיק? nesi'us mahu shetafsik?
Does becoming a king interrupt your sin? So היכי דמי, heichi dami,
what's the case? כגון, kegon, so it's a one step more complicated
than what we just said. כגון שאכל כזית חלב, kegon she'achal kezayis
chelev, thank you, there you were chomping on what you thought was
חצי כזית, chatzi kezayis, thank you, there you were chomping on what
you thought was your pastrami sandwich and it wound up being a
חלב chelev sandwich, but you thought it was pastrami, you ate a
half of a
כזית kezayis כשהוא הדיוט k'shehu hedyot and you weren't yet a king,
ונתמנה, venismaneh, and then somebody said, "Hey, you were just elected king."
Okay, ועבר, v'avar, and then they said, "Oh, forget it, whatever, we
just found a better candidate," and somehow it's not exactly clear how
they do this, it's sort of like what was that at the
Academy Awards when they gave the wrong award to the, but actually
but this wasn't a mistake, this actually was you were king for
one minute, okay, ונתמנה, venismaneh, maybe they thought that, I don't know,
you know, the father was incapacitated and then, oh, he got better.
Okay, fine. Whatever it was, ועבר, v'avar, and now you're no longer
a king. All this happens תוך כדי אכילת פרס, toch k'dei achilas
pras, all within the space of about five minutes. והשלימו, vehishlimo, and
then you say, "Thank God, now I can get back to my
sandwich." Okay, so there you ate your two half כזיתים kezaysim as
a commoner, but for one minute in between, you were a king.
Okay, so what do we say? התם הוא דלא מצטרף, hasam hu
d'lo mitztaref, so
he says והשלימו. vehishlimo. In the case we had before, it didn't
combine because half was as a commoner, half was as a king.
פלגא דהדיוט פלגא דנשיא. palga d'hedyot palga d'Nasi. אבל הכא דהאי והאי
כשהוא הדיוט אכל, aval hacha d'hai v'hai k'shehu hedyot achal, here both
halves were as a
commoner, do they combine? או דילמא o dilma or do we say
לא, lo, it doesn't matter. מאי, mai, what's the הלכה? halacha? תיפשוט
ליה, tifshot lei, this is very, this is very pressing. I got
to know the הלכה. halacha. It's very relevant. Okay. תיפשוט ליה מהא
דאמר עולא, tifshot lei meha d'amar Ulla, let's conclude it from what
עולא said. אמר רבי יוחנן: amar Rabbi Yochanan: אכל חלב והפריש קרבן
והמיר. achal chelev v'hifrish korban v'hemir.
Somebody ate חלב, chelev, he separated out his קרבן, korban. and then
he said, "That's it, I'm giving up all this religious nonsense," okay,
and he said that, "I'm not going to keep all these כשרות
kashrus laws anyway." וחזר v'chazar
and then as a מומר mumar you don't
bring a קרבן. korban So הואיל ונדחה ידחה ho'iv venidcha yidacheh since
the קרבן korban. was pushed off it remains pushed off. So that's
a principle of דחוי dichuy by קרבנות. korbanos. It passed through a
time when it couldn't be brought. So would we say the same
here? Of course there's a lot of differences. So the גמרא Gemara
says הכי השתא. hachi hashta. What type of comparison is that? מומר
לאו בר איתויי קרבן הוא. mumar lav bar asuyei korban hu. A
מומר mumar is somebody who is completely excluded from the world of
קרבנות. korbanos. האי בר איתויי קרבן הוא. hai bar asuyei korban hu.
He even as a king he was in the world of קרבנות
korbanos it just would have been a different קרבן. korban And there's
other differences too. The other difference is רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan was
very clear to say והפריש קרבן. vehifrish korban. Once the קרבן korban
is designated then the קרבן korban gets like you know stigmatized gets
pushed away and can't be reclaimed. Here the guy there was no
קרבן korban. separated. He did an act he started an act there
was a break he continued the act okay so the whole idea
of דחוי dichuy is once you have a קרבן. korban Okay so
it's a lot of differences. So we don't know. So we're going
to have to Michael I'm sorry I don't know the הלכה. Halacha.
We're going to have to go without having this without having this
important question resolved. Okay so בעי מיניה רב זירא מרב ששת. ba'ei
minei Rav Zeira meRav Sheshes. רב זירא Rav Zeira asked רב ששת.
Rav Sheshes. אכל ספק חלב כשהוא הדיוט. achal safek chelev keshehu hedyot.
Okay this is a cute one.
Somebody ate a doubtful חלב. chelev. So if they would have found
out oh my god I ate something it might have been חלב
chelev they would have brought an אשם תלוי. asham taluy. Now here's
the interesting הלכה. Halacha. An אשם תלוי asham taluy is brought for
a sin that otherwise you'd bring a חטאת chatas for. א נשיא
a nasi brings a normal אשם תלוי. asham taluy. Okay but the
underlying קרבן חטאת korban chatas that you would have brought had you
known you definitely sinned as a commoner would have been one type
of a thing a כשבה או שעירה kisba o se'irah sheep or
goat and as a נשיא nasi would have been different a male
goat. Okay but the actual אשם תלוי asham taluy is the same
as a commoner's or a הדיוט. hedyot. So if you're in the
world of אשם תלוי asham taluy and your status switches from commoner
to a I mean commoner from commoner to king
are we going to say your status in the world of אשם
תלוי asham taluy didn't switch and therefore you're going to bring the
אשם תלוי? asham taluy? Or are we going to say since the
underlying קרבן korban. on which you would bring had you were you
to know for sure you sinned had switched it's going to be
like two different statuses and you're not going to bring? Okay so
let's take a look. So אכל ספק חלב כשהוא הדיוט. achal safek
chelev keshehu hedyot.
He ate something which is doubtful חלב chelev as a commoner. ונתמנה
ונודע לו על ספיקו. venismana venoda lo al sefeko. And then he
was appointed a king and then he became aware that he actually
had eaten ספק חלב safek chelev as a commoner. מהו? mahu? What
do we say? אליבא דרבנן דאזלי בתר חטאת. aliba deRabanan de'azli basar
chatas.
According to the רבנן Rabbanan that always focus on the time of
the sin so לא תיבעי לך. lo tiba'ei lach. There's no question.
It all goes by when you sinned. When you sinned you sinned
as a commoner you were obligated as an אשם תלוי. asham taluy.
You're going to bring that. Even a נשיא nasi would even bring
a שעירה או כשבה se'irah o kisba based on what he had
done in the past as a commoner. It all goes based on
what he was at the time of the sin. דמייתי אשם תלוי.
demaytei asham taluy. You bring an אשם תלוי. asham taluy. אלא כי
תיבעי לך. ela ki tiba'ei lach. What do we want to know?
אליבא דרבי שמעון. aliba deRebbi Shimon. According to רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon.
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says you need both the sin and the
act of the sin and the awareness of the sin to have
the same you have to be in the same status in order
to be able to bring the קרבן. korban Both of those both
of those points you need the same status. So what do we
say? מידי דאשתני לוודאי אשתני לספק. midi de'ishtani levadai ishtani lesafek. Since
his status has changed in terms of what חטאת chatas he would
bring when he definitely sinned from a commoner חטאת chatas to a
נשיא חטאת. nasi chatas. So therefore an אשם תלוי asham taluy which
is brought because you don't know if you have to bring a
חטאת chatas right? It sort of has an underlying חטאת. chatas. Do
we say that your status even vis-a-vis the אשם תלוי asham taluy
changed? So it's conceptually you have a different status and therefore you
don't bring an אשם תלוי. asham taluy. או דלמא o dilma or
do we say כי אשתני לוודאי דאשתני קרבן דידיה. ki ishtani levadai
de'ishtani korban dideih. No when it comes to sinning definitely definitely sinning
then you have a different status and if you sinned as a
commoner and now you became aware as a נשיא nasi you don
bring a קרבן korban because as a commoner you have one type
of a קרבן korban and as a נשיא nasi a different one.
אבל הכא דלא אשתני קרבן דידיה. aval hacha dela ishtani korban dideih.
But as an אשם תלוי asham taluy the קרבן korban. is the
same as a commoner and a king even though the underlying קרבן
חטאת korban chatas is different. So אימא ליתי אשם תלוי. eima leisei
asham taluy. Maybe you should bring an אשם תלוי. asham taluy. תיקו.
teiku. So we're not going to know the answer to that. Okay
תנו רבנן. tanu Rabanan. מעם הארץ. me'am ha'aretz. Now we get to
this now. So we've excluded from עם הארץ am ha'aretz a מומר
mumar and a נשיא nassi. and had some fun with a נשיא
nassi about half and half and you know you being a king
in the middle and all these types of questions. Now we get
to this other very more common sort of line that's quoted which
we about this idea of a מומר mumar and a מומר mumar
being excluded from קרבנות. korbanos. Okay let's take a look.
תנו רבנן מעם הארץ פרט למומר. tanu Rabanan me'am ha'aretz perat lemumar.
רבי שמעון ברבי יוסי אומר משום רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon beRebbi Yosi
omer mishum Rebbi Shimon. אשר לא תעשנה בשגגה ואשם. asher lo se'asenah
bishgaga ve'ashem. He sort of gets to the same point or close
to the same point by saying the following פסוק. passuk That it
says if somebody does a sin which should not be done and
they did it in error and is and sort of and you
know has guilt or is blameworthy then brings this קרבן. korban
So his דרשה is אשר לא תעשנה. asher lo se'asenah. Had I
known better I wouldn't have done it. השב בידיעה. hashav biyedi'ah. ועשה
מביא קרבן על שגגתו, V’asoh meivi korban al shegagato, somebody who would
have
withheld himself, not acted that way had
they become had they known better, that’s the type of person that
brings a קרבן korban for for his mistaken sin. לא שב בידיעתו,
Lo shav biyediato, somebody who would not have retracted his action had
he known
better, אינו מביא קרבן על שגגתו. eino meivi korban al shegagato. So
the case is like this: here’s this מומר mumar who doesn’t care
about eating חלב, chelev, but he eats something thinking it’s שומן shuman
and it accidentally turns out to be חלב. chelev. So here’s a
guy that would have been happily eating חלב chelev anyway, but in
this particular circumstance his eating of חלב chelev was an accident. Does
he bring a שוגג? shogeg? Okay, so obviously you understand it seems
like absurd. Here’s a guy that doesn’t care about doing it willfully,
why should he be bringing a חטאת chatas as a שוגג? shogeg?
But that’s our question. So both of these positions says he doesn’t,
but for different reasons. One does it based on an issue of
personal status. Since בגברא, begavra, as we would say, your status is
as a מומר, mumar, you’re excluded from the world of קרבנות. korbanot.
The other says, I don’t focus on the personal status, I focus
on the action. Since it’s a sin that you that the only
sin that you bring a קרבן korban for is a sin that
otherwise you you would you personally would not have done had you
known better. Okay, here, since you would have been prepared to do
it even had you known better, it’s not that it’s not an
action that you bring a קרבן korban for. So the גמרא Gemara
wants to know, what’s the difference from the what practical difference emerges
from these two approaches? So the גמרא Gemara says, איכא בינייהו, ikka
beinaihu, so here’s the practical difference. מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? What difference?
Says there, אמר רב המנונא: Amar Rav Hamnuna: מומר לאכול חלב ומביא
קרבן על דם איכא בינייהו. mumar l’echol chelev umeivi korban al dam
ikka beinaihu. The difference would be somebody who has rejected the world
of you know the the prohibition of חלב, chelev, a forbidden fat,
but the sin was a different sin, it was eating blood. Okay,
so if you focus on personal status, we could say since in
one area of הלכה halacha you’re a מומר, mumar, you’ve rejected one
area of the law, that gives you the personal status of a
מומר mumar and therefore you’ll never bring a קרבן korban. on any
sin, even even for the מצוות mitzvos that you’re keeping. That’s if
I focus on your personal status. Whereas if I focus on your
action, since you like you do keep the prohibition of blood and
you wouldn’t have eaten it had you known better, you’ll still bring
a
קרבן. korban. Okay, מר סבר כיון דמומר לאכול חלב, Mar savar keivan
de’mumar l’echol chelev, since this person has a personal status of a
מומר mumar when it comes to חלב, chelev, לדם נמי מומר הוי,
l’dam nami mumar havei, you’re also considered a מומר mumar for all
areas. Once once you’re a מומר, mumar, you’re completely excluded. ומר סבר,
U-mar savar, and the other says, no, we look at the individual
action. לדם מיהו, L'dam mihu, this act of eating blood, שב בידיעתו
הוא, shav biyediato hu, it’s something he rather would not have done.
So that’s we could understand that, but the obvious question you should
be asking is, why if somebody’s a מומר mumar in one area
does he have a global status of a מומר? mumar? Which is
exactly what the גמרא Gemara pushes back. ורבא אמר דכולי עלמא מומר
לאכול חלב לא הוי מומר לדם, Ve-Rava amar de'chulei alma mumar l’echol
chelev lo havei mumar l’dam, but רבא Rava says no, even according
to both opinions, if somebody is just rejecting one area of law,
that doesn’t affect their personal status in another area. Like you know
we might say that if somebody’s a מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, then
they’re considered excluded for all areas because that’s something that sort of
like represents the entire system, or מומר mumar for עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. But if we’re talking about a מומר mumar for some narrower
area that doesn’t affect your status in a different one. So in
the world of דם, dam, you’re not a מומר, mumar, and therefore
you would bring a קרבן. korban So that’s not a good app
you know difference between the two approaches. So the גמרא says, אלא
הכא באוכל נבילה לתיאבון ונתחלף לו בשומן ואכלו קמיפלגי. ela hacha be’ochel
neveilah l’teiavon u’nischalef lo be’shuman ve’achalo kamifligi. So the question is, why
are you a מומר? mumar? What type of a מומר mumar are
you? מומר להכעיס mumar l’hachis or מומר לתיאבון? mumar l’teiavon? Okay, a
מומר להכעיס mumar l’hachis is somebody who basically says, I completely reject
this, and is and even if it’s you have kosher meat and
טריפה treifa meat, they have absolutely no pre they have so completely
rejected it that they that they would eat the טריפה treifa meat
even if they could just eat the kosher meat just as easily.
Where that’s a מומר להכעיס. mumar l’hachis. A מומר לתיאבון mumar l’teiavon
is somebody that basically, no, at some level they’d rather be keeping
kosher, it’s just, you know, they’re not going to spend an extra
dollar for it in the store, or if it tastes better they’re
going to eat the טריפה treif stuff, but all things being equal
they’ll eat they’ll prefer they’ll choose the kosher meat over the טריפה
treifa meat. Okay, so they’re not completely rejecting it, they’re just rejecting
it because, you know, it’s not important as as important to them
as a lot of other considerations. Okay, that’s a מומר לתיאבון. mumar
l’teiavon. So now, here’s the case. So somebody was a מומר לתיאבון,
mumar l’teiavon, and they went ahead and they ate this חלב chelev
thinking it was שומן. shuman. Okay, so so how do they do
they bring a קרבן korban for eating חלב? chelev? So let’s take
a look. Okay, באוכל נבילה לתיאבון ונתחלף לו בשומן ואכלו קמיפלגי. be’ochel
neveilah l’teiavon u’nischalef lo be’shuman ve’achalo kamifligi. It’s actually not נבילה, neveilah,
you don’t bring a קרבן korban, for נבילה, neveilah, it would be
חלב chelev but the standard phrase is
אוכל נבילה. ochel neveilah. Okay, מר סבר כיון דלתיאבון אכיל במזיד מומר
הוא. mar savar keivan de’l’teiavon achil be’mezid mumar hu. One says, look,
here’s a guy that is will that that regularly eats טריפות treifus
במזיד, be’mezid, and therefore he is considered and he ate טריפות treifus
now, so in the world of טריפות treifus he is
a מומר. mumar. טריפות *treifas* even by accident he doesn't bring a
קרבן korban *korban*. This is a world that he doesn't get to
bring קרבנות korbanot *korbanos* for because he willfully violates all the time.
That's one opinion. ומר סבר *U'mar savar* the other one holds כיון
דאי לאו אשכח דהיתירא לא אכל דאיסורא *keivan d'ee lo ishchach d'heteira
lo achal d'issura*. No, he hasn't completely rejected. If he, if he,
if he would find some היתר *heter* meat which would be just
as, you know, good as the טריפה *treif* meat and just as
cheap as the טריפה *treif* meat or whatever and he would eat
it לאו מומר mumar. הוא *lav mumar hu*. He's not a מומר
mumar *mumar*. And not only is he not a מומר mumar. *mumar*
because he hasn't completely rejected but also he's a שב מידיעתו *shav
mi'yadiaso*. Here's a guy chomping on a שומן *shuman* sandwich and if
you tell him wait don't eat it it's חלב cheilev, *cheilev* is
he going to say I don't care because I don't care about
all these laws or is he going to say oh do you
have a שומן *shuman* sandwich that you can give me instead? Sure
here's a שומן *shuman* sandwich. Then he says fine I'll take that.
If you say no I don't have a שומן *shuman* sandwich then
he says then don't bother me and he'll keep on eating. But
since he would be שב מידיעתו *shav mi'yadiaso* he would stop doing
it if he was given a, you know, a reasonable alternative, the
option to eat כשר *kosher*, that's considered enough that he sinned in
error. He would rather have not have sinned and therefore he's going
to bring a קרבן korban? *korban*. But if you deal with the
personal status of a מומר mumar *mumar* he's a מומר mumar. *mumar*
for this area and he doesn't bring a קרבן korban *korban*. Okay
so now the גמרא *Gemara* continues. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan: *Tano rabanan*.
There was a very interesting like difference there. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan,
*Tano rabanan*. אוכל חלב cheilev, זהו מומר mumar, *Ochel cheilev zehu mumar*.
Somebody eats חלב cheilev *cheilev* he's a מומר mumar, *mumar*. ואיזהו מומר
mumar, *V'eizehu mumar* and who's a מומר mumar. *mumar*? אוכל נבילות וטריפות
שקצים ורמשים *Ochel nevelos v'treifos shekatzim u'remasim* if somebody eats נבילות *nevelos*,
you know, dead animals, and טריפות *treifas* ones with injuries and bugs
and whatever and you know and creepy crawlies ושתה יין נסך *v'shosei
yein nesech* and drinks יין נסך *yein nesech*. So like it gave
two definitions one right after the other. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda
omer, *Rabbi Yehuda omer* אף הלובש כלאים kilayim. *af ha'lovesh kilayim* even
if somebody wears כלאים kilayim *kilayim* they're a מומר mumar. *mumar*. So
like what the heck is going on here? אמר מר amar mar.
*Amar mar* אוכל חלב זהו מומר mumar, *Ochel cheilev zehu mumar*. If
you eat חלב *cheilev* you're a מומר mumar. *mumar*. ואיזהו מומר *V'eizehu
mumar*? Who's a מומר *mumar*? אוכל נבילות *Ochel nevelos* etc. מאי קאמר
*Mai kama*? What are you saying? First you said here it is
and then you defined it again. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי Rebbi יוחנן הכי קאמר *Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan hachi kama* אוכל חלב לתיאבון leteiavon. *ochel cheilev l'teiavon* if you
eat חלב *cheilev* because out of appetite desire הרי זה zeh מומר
*harei zeh mumar*. That's a normal מומר *mumar*. Somebody who does it
that they're, you know, they're ready to sin if it's more attractive
to sin. But they're not completely rejecting it. Okay
they're sinning out of appetite and out of, you know, lust and
so on. להכעיס lehach'is. *L'hachis*. But if somebody sins in to spite
that they'll even do it even if it's just as, you know,
it's just as attractive to do the מצוה *mitzvah* they're going to
do the עבירה *aveirah* הרי זה *harei zeh* now our גירסא *girsa*
is צדוקי *tzeduki* but the original גירסא *girsa* is מין min, *min*.
Okay this person is a מין min, *min* which is like an
apostate or a sectarian. This is somebody who has more fundamentally rejected
the system. It's not like you buy into the system but you
don't have a strong enough will to live up to it okay
or you have, you know, other priorities it's that you have fundamentally
rejected. The reason it gets sort of censored out the word מין
min. *min* is because מין min? *min* in the Christian era referred
to, you know, Jews who would who converted to Christianity. And therefore
Jews didn't want to get in trouble, you know, by there being
things in the גמרא *Gemara* that were read to refer to Christians
or to Christian apostates and so on. So there was a whole
period of like, you know, censoring those words. But anyway the word
is מין min. *min*. Okay מומר ומין *mumar v'min* are the usual
two that are side by side. מומר *mumar* is somebody who's sort
of like has rejected, doesn't do a certain area of law but
מין min. *min* is a more principled rejection. Okay so that's the
basic distinction. But so a normal one who's doing it לתיאבון *l'teiavon*
is a מומר *mumar*. ואיזהו מומר דבסתמא מין *V'eizehu mumar d'bistama min*?
Who would be a מומר *mumar* that we would presume is a
מין *min*? That's doing it just to spite? Okay? ההוא אומר אוכל
נבילות טריפות שקצים ורמשים ושתה יין נסך *ha'hu omer ochel nevelos treifos
shekatzim u'remasim v'shosei yein nesech*. A person that eats these types of
things. Now why do we assume that person is doing it to
spite? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says well these things are not things
that there's necessarily a desire for. Why? Well a נבילה *neveila* if
you assume a נבילה *neveila* doesn't just mean meat that was shechted
improperly but you assume a נבילה *neveila* means like an animal that
actually like died out of an illness okay it dropped dead because
it was old and whatever that's disgusting. Why would you eat it?
If you're going to eat it you're going to only eat it
out of spite. טריפה *Treifa* is difficult because why is a טריפה
*treifa* an animal with some internal injury something that's not attractive or
desirable to be eaten? הרא"ש *The Rosh* suggests that maybe the גירסא
*girsa* doesn't have the word טריפה *treifa*. He's bothered with that. שקצים
ורמשים *shekatzim u'remasim* that's easy you know bugs and creepy crawlies and
rodents. You could say the only reason you're eating that is out
of spite. But how about יין נסך *yein nesech*? How about wine?
What do you mean the only reason you're eating that is out
of spite? Maybe the non-Jewish wine is cheaper than the Jewish wine
you know? So he says well if it's literally wine that was
poured to עבודה avoda זרה *avoda zara* that really would take somebody
who really, you know, that's so repulsive to a normal פרום *frum*
Jew that that really would take somebody who really like rejected something
out of principle. But it's hard to read it in why these
things. Some of these things seem to be things you could do
even if you're not a principled
rejector. Okay so
that's the basic distinction. Oh, the other thing that the ראש says
is the following: he says it doesn't mean, and I don't know
if he can really, it's hard to read this in the words,
because the words say, but he says maybe it also means somebody
who does it all the time, not just that has done it,
you know, once in a while. But anyway, nevertheless, maybe you do
it all the time because maybe, I don't know, you have an
appetite for it or maybe the non-kosher wine is cheaper and the
non-kosher meat is cheaper. So it's not exactly clear why we're assuming
that these things are cases that they're disgusting, but that's somehow the
assumption. This, you know, when you're dealing with certain עבירות aveiros that
there's no יצר הרע yeitzer hara for and somebody is still doing
it, then we're going to interpret that as a type of להכעיס.
lehach'is, But how that exactly fits this case is less clear. Okay,
so now the גמרא says like this. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda omer, now the last one, אף הלוביש כלאים,
Af halo vash Kilayim, even somebody who wears כלאים. kilayim, Now is
that clarifying the case of מומר לתיאבון mumar lete'avon or מומר להכעיס?
mumar lehach'is? רש"י Rashi says it's going on the case of מומר
לתיאבון mumar lete'avon and saying not only somebody who, I don't know,
eats חלב, even somebody who wears כלאים kilayim, is also a מומר
לתיאבון. mumar lete'avon. So okay, you're both saying somebody who does an
עבירה is a מומר. So מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what's the difference?
איכא בינייהו כלאים דרבנן. ika beinaihu kilayim derabbanan. Since you said כלאים,
kilayim, you know, when you say somebody eats חלב, חלב is clearly
a דאורייתא de'oraisa sin. So that approach would say somebody is only
a מומר if they do a biblical sin. When you say כלאים,
kilayim? there are plenty of examples of דרבנן derabbanan כלאים, kilayim. like
let's say it's not literally wool and linen, you know, woven together,
let's say it's just like one on top of the other, like
a type of a felt or pressed together. So even so, this
one is saying even if it's only a דרבנן derabbanan sin, you
could still be a מומר. מר סבר מדאורייתא הוי מומר דרבנן לא
הוי מומר, mar savar mide'oraisa havei mumar derabbanan lo havei mumar,
you're only a מומר for violating a biblical sin, ומר סבר כלאים
כיון דמפרסם איסוריה, umar savar kilayim keivan demefarsam issurei,
since everybody knows about the prohibition of שעטנז, shatnez, אפילו בדרבנן הוי
מומר, afilu bederabbanan havei mumar,
even if you regularly violate that, you know, you are considered to
be a מומר. Again, רש"י Rashi says we're dealing about מומר לתיאבון
mumar lete'avon here. The ראש suggests maybe we're even talking about מומר
להכעיס mumar lehach'is because like what's the יצר הרע yeitzer hara to
wear כלאים? kilayim If there's no יצר הרע yeitzer hara and you're
doing it anyway, of course maybe the יצר הרע yeitzer hara is
you don't like to get your suits checked and have to go
through the problem or whatever, maybe the nice attractive suit you want
to get is כלאים. kilayim. So anyway, but so רש"י Rashi reads
it that we're talking about it within the מומר לתיאבון mumar lete'avon
category.
Okay, why do they call כלאים kilayim דרבנן? derabbanan?
No, an example when there is an example of דרבנן derabbanan כלאים.
An example of דרבנן derabbanan כלאים would be let's say you had
wool and linen pressed together and not woven together. So in a
circumstance of that. Okay, so you have this idea though that there's
a מומר לתיאבון, mumar lete'avon, which is that you just do it
because, you know, you have other priorities. Okay, and then you have
a מומר להכעיס, mumar lehach'is, which is a principled rejection, which is
obviously a more fundamental, which is a
מין, which is a more fundamental sort of, you know, category of
exclusion. So now the גמרא says like this. פליגי בה רב אחא
ורבינא, pligi bah Rav Acha u-Ravina, this issue of מומר, פליגי בה
רב אחא ורבינא. pligi bah Rav Acha u-Ravina. חד אמר
לתיאבון מומר, chad amar lete'avon mumar, somebody who just does it for
desire is a מומר, להכעיס, mumar lehach'is if somebody is a principled
rejecter, מין, then that doesn't give you any more the status of
a מומר, then you're more fundamentally outside of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael,
you know, fundamentally excluded, and that's considered a מין. וחד אמר להכעיס
נמי מומר, vechad amar lehach'is nami mumar, even if
somebody does it להכעיס lehach'is they're just a מומר. Okay, even a
principled rejection, you're still fundamentally in the body of כלל ישראל. Klal
Yisrael. You know, there's ways you're excluded, you don't bring a קרבן,
korban you don't whatever, but it's not as fundamental of a putting
you outside. אלא
איזהו מין, ela eizehu min, what would be a מין?
כל העובד עבודת כוכבים. kol ha-oved avodat kochavim. You have to really
reject the entire system. Okay, it's not just enough that you are
מומר להכעיס lehach'is when it comes to חמץ בפסח chametz be-pesach or
בשר בחלב basar be-chalav or whatever. Okay, people have their particular areas
and their שטויות shtuyot or whatever. That doesn't put you fundamentally outside.
You would have to really reject the whole thing. You'd have to
be עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah.
מתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on the idea that a להכעיס lehach'is.
is a מין. אכל פרעוש אחד או יתוש אחד הרי זה מומר.
achal parosh echad o yatush echad harei zeh mumar. We have a
ברייתא baraisa that says if somebody eats like one type of a
bug or a fly or whatever this is, a gnat, they're a
מומר. Okay, so that, so that's a disgusting thing. So the only
reason a person would do that would be להכעיס. lehach'is And it
still says he's a מומר, not a מין. That supports the, you
know, that the second opinion that even להכעיס lehachis, is only a
מומר. דהכא דלהכעיס הוא וקא קרי ליה מומר. de-hacha de-lehach'is hu ve-ka
kari leih mumar. So the גמרא says no, התם דאמר אטעם טעמא
דאיסורא. hatam de-amar eiteim tama de-issura. Just because somebody
wants to do something just once, they're just being like a, you
know, what's it called, there's a word, adventurous, no, not adventurous, there's
another word. Anyway, but they're trying to, you know, they're trying to
just get the taste of
something, you know, something forbidden to them, so they did it once.
So even if it's disgusting, they maybe just doing it to have
some experience, okay. They're not doing it דוקא להכעיס. davka lehach'is. Maybe
if they did it it all the time it would be להכעיס,
but doing it once they could still be doing it לתיאבון. Okay,
now back to, that was a fun little digression, back to the
issue of the קרבן korban of the נשיא. nassi, איזהו נשיא, eizehu
nassi, who is the נשיא nassi, that brings the קרבן? זהו מלך,
zeh melech, it’s a king. תנו רבנן: נשיא, nassi, שנאמר אם נשיא
יחטא. shene’emar im nassi yecheta. יכול נשיא שבט כנחשון בן עמינדב? yachol
nassi shevet ke-Nachshon ben Amminadav? Maybe just the head of a tribe?
תלמוד לומר מכל מצות ה' אלקיו, talmud lomar mikkol mitzvot Hashem Elokav,
any of the mitzvot of ה' Hashem his God. ולהלן הוא אומר,
u-lehallan hu omer, and by the king it says למען ילמד ליראה
את ה' אלקיו, lema’an yilmad leyirah et Hashem Elokav, so that he
will fear ה' Hashem his God. מה להלן שאין על גביו אלא
ה' אלקיו, mah lehallan she’ein al gabav ella Hashem Elokav, the same
way over there it means the only power or authority above him
is ה' Hashem his God, אף נשיא שאין על גביו אלא ה'
אלקיו, af nassi she’ein al gabav ella Hashem Elokav, even the נשיא,
nassi the only authority above him is ה' Hashem his God. Okay,
so meaning a king. So בעי מיניה רבי מרבי חייא: ba’i minei
Rebbi me-Rebbi Chiya: כגון אני בשעיר. kegon ani be-seir. Am I, if
there was a בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, would I be considered like
a king to bring a שעיר? seir? Now this is tied into
the whole idea that רבי Rebbi is understood to be a descendant
of the Davidic line, so he wasn't just that he was a
נשיא, but there was an idea that he was from בית דוד,
Beit David? so that’s an interesting question. How much does the idea
of a king have to have that idea of בית דוד? Beit
David? That’s nowhere in the פסוק. שאול Shaul in theory could have
brought this, who says you need to be from בית דוד? Maybe
מלכות ישראל malchut Yisrael could bring it, which we’ll get to in
a minute. Okay, so anyway, but it is important to note that
רבי Rebbi did understand himself to be a descendant of the Davidic
line. So he said, do I have enough political power now to,
to what degree do you need the formal status of king or
is it seems to be what it’s asking or would be anybody
that would be in the ultimate position of political power? One minute.
Also could be a question about what do you do about the
fact that Israel was still under Roman rule. So that doesn’t seem
to be asked, of course that could be asked as well. So
let’s see what the answer was. אמר ליה, amar leh, הרי צרתך
בבבל. harei tzaratka be-Bavel. You’re not the ultimate authority over the Jewish
people, you have a competitor, like a צרה tzarah is a competitor
wife, you have a competitor in בבל. Bavel. The ריש גלותא Reish
Galuta of בבל Bavel is the head political authority of the Jews
in גלות, Galut, of the Jews outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
So you are not the sole authority of the Jewish people. איתיבי,
eitivei, I’ll ask you on this. מלכי ישראל ומלכי בית דוד אלו
מביאים לעצמן ואלו מביאים לעצמן. malchei Yisrael u-malchei Beit David, eleh mevivim
le-atzman ve-eleh mevivim le-atzman. Here you go, king of ישראל Yisrael and
Davidic kings, they would each bring a שעיר seir if they had
sinned, which means, A, you don’t have to be part of the
Davidic line, but it also means you don’t have to be king
of the entire Jewish people. Even if you’re king only of two
tribes or of ten tribes, you bring, you don’t have to be
over all the Jewish people. So the גמרא says, אמר ליה, amar
leh, התם לא חייפי הדדי. hatam lo chayfya hadadei. There one is
not subject to the other, they each have their own מלכותא. malchuta.
הכא אנן חייפינן להו לדידהו. hacha anan chayfinan le-hu le-didehu. Here we
ultimately actually have, are subject to the authority of the political leadership
of בבל, Bavel, which is very strange, that where is that idea
that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they were subject to the political
leadership, I mean they are subject to the political authority of Rome,
but anyway, let’s keep on reading. רב ספרא מתני הכי, Rav Safra
matni hachi, one minute, בעי מיניה ba’i minei רבי Rebbi מרבי חייא:
me-Rebbi Chiya: כגון אני בשעיר. kegon ani be-seir. אמר ליה, amar leh,
התם שבט הכא מחוקק. hatam shevet hacha mechokek. This maybe helps clarify
a little. There in בבל Bavel they have actual, their political authority
actually is much more like שבט shevet using the rod, like they
have real power, they can send the police, we have these stories
about the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta sending his thugs and the police
after people and so on. Here your authority is more as a
מחוקק, mechokek, a lawgiver. Yes maybe you have political authority, but not
so much with a police force behind you. Okay, דתניא, de-tanya, לא
יסור שבט מיהודה, lo yasur shevet mi-Yehudah, זה ריש גלותא שבבבל. zeh
Reish Galuta she-be-Bavel. The staff should not be removed from יהודה, so
the staff is like the physical power, that’s the head of גולה
Golah in בבל Bavel שרודה את ישראל במקל, she-rodeh et Yisrael be-makkel,
and the lawgiver ומחוקק u-mechokek מבין רגליו, mibbein raglav, אלו בני בניו
של הלל, eilu bnei vanav shel Hillel, these are the descendants of
הלל Hillel שמלמדים תורה לישראל ברבים, she-melammedim Torah le-Yisrael be-rabbim, they teach
תורה, Torah but that, this answer seems to actually even completely reframe
it. It actually says that רבי Rebbi really, you should just be
seeing yourself as the head rabbinic authority, you shouldn’t be looking at
yourself as the head political authority. I mean, that’s a little bit
stark. רבי Rebbi was, the whole idea in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
was that the נשיא was the combination which you didn’t have in
בבל, Bavel, the combination of the political and the תורה Torah authority.
This is saying, no, fundamentally you’re just a תורה authority. The other
answer seemed to be, yes, you’re a political authority, but you are
somehow subject to the authority in בבל. Bavel. I don't really understand
that, like, I didn't know that to be the case at all,
that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was subject to בבל. Bavel. They were
subject to Rome. So I don’t understand what חייפינן להדדי chayfinan le-hadadei
means. What did you want to say, Michal? It’s written by the
בבלי. Bavli. Yes, that’s also true. What’s the version of this in
the ירושלמי? Yerushalmi? Does this exist? Right, that absolutely. This is serious.
רבי is at a time where I think בבל Bavel is not
yet authoritative. That’s a good point, that the more of the rabbinic
of the right, I mean you obviously had a significant Jewish population
in בבל Bavel even at the time of the תנאים, Tannaim, but
a lot of them were sort of going to ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, so I don’t know. I don't know if David, you could
see if the footnotes say anything about כפינן ליה, Kofinan leh, if
they have any theory about that. Yeah, two things. One, this brings
up the question what about the king who was also a כהן
גדול, Cohen Gadol, which was some of the חשמונאים? Hashmonaim? Right, that's
interesting. Which קרבן would he bring? Yeah, that's a good question. And
the other thing is Rome didn't have a king. They had an
emperor who they were very adamant was not a king. Yeah, that
I know. But anyway, it doesn't matter though, the question is is
Rebbe considered a king and how much do you need the title?
I mean, he's not called a king. Anyway, it seems clear that
you don't need the title of king, that's because the פסוק doesn't
say king, it says השם אלוקיך, Hashem Elokecha, so you need the
title, you need to be the ultimate authority, right? Okay, let's keep
going, and that explains most of the kings of Judea were evil,
all the kings of Israel were evil. Alright, let's read a little
bit further. Okay, ואיזהו משיח. Ve'eizehu Mashiach. Now, you can tell somebody
when somebody says to you, what did you learn in the דף
today, you could say, I learned a משנה Mishna that started with
the words, 'Who is the Mashiach?' Okay. ואיזהו המשיח, Ve'eizehu haMashiach, who
is the Mashiach? And look at this, the next line to that
says הרבי מליובאוויטש. haRebbe miLubavitch. I can't believe it. המשיח, haMashiach, okay.
So who is the כהן המשיח? Cohen haMashiach? המשוח בשמן המשחה, Hamashuach
beshemen hamishcha, the one who is anointed with the oil of anointing,
the כהן גדול, Cohen Gadol, only that כהן גדול. Cohen Gadol. לא
מרובה בגדים, Lo merubeh begadim, not a כהן גדול Cohen Gadol who
is a full כהן גדול, Cohen Gadol, but who lived in a
time when they lost the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha and they didn't
do the appointment and they didn't do the sort of, you know,
investiture through the anointment, only through wearing the garments of the כהן
גדול. Cohen Gadol. Even though that person is a full כהן גדול,
Cohen Gadol, he does not bring the special קרבן because this is
a קרבן brought by the משיח, Mashiach, the one who is anointed.
אין בין כהן המשיח בשמן המשחה למרובה בגדים. Ein bein Cohen haMashiach
beshemen hamishcha lemerubeh begadim. This is from the משנה Mishna in מגילה.
Megilla. There's no difference between the כהן Cohen anointed and the כהן
Cohen with who's just becomes a כהן גדול Cohen Gadol through the
clothes, through the vestments, אלא פר הבא על כל המצוות. ela par
haba al kol hamitzvot. This is the difference, whether you bring this
special ox when you do an עבירה. ואין בין כהן משמש לכהן
שעבר. Ve'ein bein Cohen meshamesh lechohen she'avar. There's no difference between the
serving כהן Cohen and a כהן Cohen that is passed. The past
כהן Cohen is somebody who, as רש"י Rashi points out, took the
place of the כהן גדול Cohen Gadol on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
because something happened to the כהן גדול. Cohen Gadol. Then when the
כהן גדול Cohen Gadol is now fit to serve, the old כהן
גדול Cohen Gadol goes back and the one who served like just
for the day is called the כהן שעבר. Cohen she'avar. But the
standard כהן גדול Cohen Gadol resumes his post. Okay, so anyway, the
serving כהן Cohen and the one who was, who is no longer
serving, there's no difference כהן גדול, Cohen Gadol, אלא פר יום הכיפורים
ועשירית האיפה. ela par Yom haKippurim va'asirit ha'eifa. Who brings the ox
on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? The ox on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
is brought only by the כהן גדול Cohen Gadol himself, the serving
כהן גדול. Cohen Gadol. It's interesting, רש"י sounds like you can have
the other כהן גדול, Cohen Gadol, the past כהן גדול, Cohen Gadol,
do some of the other קרבנות on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But
in terms of who's bringing the ox for the כהנים, Kohanim, that's
only the current serving כהן גדול. Cohen Gadol. And the tenth of
the איפה, eifa, the מנחה mincha that was brought by the כהן
גדול Cohen Gadol each day, half in the morning and half in
the afternoon. Okay, וזה וזה שוים בעבודת יום הכיפורים. vezeh vezeh shavin
ba'avodat Yom haKippurim. Both of them can do all other parts of
the עבודה on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So imagine that, you would
have two כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim working on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you know, one but one only one of them can bring the,
can bring the special ox. So you know, only one, I mean,
the only the serving one can bring the special ox. ומצווים על
הבתולה, Umetzuvim al habetulah, have to marry a virgin, a woman who
is a virgin. ואסורים על האלמנה, Ve'asurim al ha'almanah, cannot marry a
widow. ואינם מיטמאים בקרוביהם, Ve'einam mitam'im bikroveihem, cannot become טמא tamei even
if their immediate relatives die. Meaning they have all the other הלכות
halachot of a כהן גדול. Cohen Gadol. ולא פורעים ולא פורמים, Velo
por'im velo pormim, if somebody dies they do not let their hair
grow wild, they don't rend their garments. ומחזירים את הרוצח, Umachzirin et
harotzeach, and if they die, the murderer would come back. So presumably
it means even if one כהן גדול Cohen Gadol dies and the
other one is alive, okay, since somebody with the status of a
כהן גדול Cohen Gadol died, that would actually allow the murderer to
come back from the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. Okay, I know it's
already 8:30 but I'm just, if you can give me five more
minutes we'll just cover, we can cover a significant amount of space
here. תנו רבנן, ground. שמן המשחה שעשה משה במדבר, Shemen hamishcha she'asa
Moshe bamidbar, the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha that משה Moshe made, היו
שולקים בו את העיקרים. hayu sholkim bo et ha'ikarim. What they would
do is that they would sort of boil the oil, which is
the twelve לוג log of oil, in all of the various herbs
or whatever or fragrances, the roots of these plants that the Torah
indicates that you would use to make the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishcha,
this fragrant oil. דברי רבי יהודה, Divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said. רבי יוסי אומר ולא לשלוק את העיקרים היה
סופק. Rabbi Yossi omer velo lishlok et ha'ikarim hayah sofek. How could
you boil it in the oil? There's such little oil and so
many of these plants that even just to sort of to sort
of rub it on the plants, there's not enough oil. So how
do you think you could boil it, all the, you know, you'd
have no oil left. אלא שורין את העיקרים במים, Ela shorin et
ha'ikarim bamayim, first what you do is that you get them to,
you submerge the, these roots in water, so they get totally filled
with water so now they can't absorb too much oil, okay, because
they're already filled with liquid. ומציף עליהם שמן, Umetzif aleihem shemen, and
then you take the roots out of the water, you put the
oil on top of the roots, and then it doesn't get absorbed.
into the roots because they're filled with water, but it, the oil,
you know, absorbs, takes on the fragrance from the roots, וקולט את
הריח, vekolet et hareiach, it absorbs the fragrance of the roots, וקפחו
vekapcho and then you sort of and then you collect the oil
right away. אמר ליה רבי יהודה Amar lei Rabbi Yehuda so Rabbi
Yehuda responded back to to this to Rabbi Yose who said how
could you do it? There's not enough oil. And he said, what
do you, you know, what are you asking me practical? It was
a miracle. וכי נס אחד נעשה בשמן המשחה? vechi nes echad na’asah
beshemen hamishchah? Do you think there was only one miracle done with
the oil? הלא תחילתו שנים עשר לוג, halo techilato shenem asar log,
it started being only 12 log, וממנו היה נמשך umimenu hayah nimshach
and think how much of it you used. You would anoint from
it, so this is last week's Parsha, whatever, not just last week,
the previous Parsha. נמשך משכן וכליו אהרן ובניו, nimshach mishkan vechelav Aharon
uvanav, you did the the the Mishkan, all the vessels, Aaron, the
kids, ובניו כל שבעת ימי המילואים uvanav kol shivat yemei hamiluim for
all seven days. So you probably would have used it up already
three times. And nevertheless, וכולו קיים לעתיד לבוא, vechulo kayam le’atid lavo,
the whole 12 log not only remained after all of that, but
they are going to even remain, they're all waiting for us for
the future. שנאמר שמן משחת קודש יהיה זה לי לדורותיכם, shene’emar shemen
mishchat kodesh yihyeh zeh li ledoroteichem, and the drashah is going to
be we'll see in a minute. זה Gematria is 12. So the
12 will be, you'll still have the 12 log even for future
generations. תני אידך tani idach we taught another Baraita, ויקח משה את
שמן המשחה וימשח את המשכן ואת כל אשר בו. vayikach Moshe et
shemen hamishchah vayimshach et hamishkan ve’et kol asher bo. רבי יהודה אומר,
שמן המשחה שעשה משה במדבר כמה ניסים נעשו בו. shemen hamishchah she’asah
Moshe bamidbar kamah nissim na’asu vo. How many miracles? מתחילה ועד סוף.
mitchilah ve’ad sof. תחילתו לא היה אלא שנים עשר לוג, techilato lo
hayah ela shenem asar log, it was only 12 log to begin
with. וראה כמה יורה בולעו, ure’eh kamah yoreh bole’o, how much gets
absorbed when you when you boil it, because he said it would
be done by boiling. וכמה עיקרין בולעין, vechamah ikarin bol’in, and the
roots would absorb again because he didn't say that you would first
submerge the roots in water. וכמה אור שורפת, vechamah or sorefet, how
much is burned by the fire. ובו נמשך משכן וכליו אהרן ובניו
כל שבעת ימי המילואים. uvo nimshach mishkan vechelav Aharon uvanav kol shivat
yemei hamiluim. Okay. ובו נמשכו כהנים גדולים ומלכים, uvo nimsh'chu kohanim gedolim
umelachim, and he goes on. Not only was it done for the
seven days of miluim, it was used in future generations for Kohen
Gadol and for kings. ואפילו כהן גדול בן כהן גדול טעון משיחה,
ve’afilu kohen gadol ben kohen gadol ta’un meshichah, even a Kohen Gadol
the son of a Kohen Gadol, you would appoint him in this
position through anointing. ואין מושחים מלך בן מלך, ve’ein mosh’chin melech ben
melech, parenthetically because now we're getting into the laws of how you
use the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishchah. You would not use it to
anoint the king the son of a king. ואם תאמר מפני מה
משחו את שלמה, ve’im tomar mipnei mah mash’chu et Shlomo, so why
did they anoint Shlomo if he was the son of a king?
מפני מחלוקתו של אדוניה, mipnei machlokto shel Adoniyah, because his kingship was
being contested by Adoniyah. So you'd have to anoint him to to
make it very clear, you need the ritual to show who the
next king is. But if it's clear who the next king is,
you don't do the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishchah. ואת יהואש מפני עתליה,
ve’et Yehoash mipnei Atalyah, they anointed Yehoash because of Atalyah. ואת יהואחז
מפני יהויקים. ve’et Yehoachaz mipnei Yehoyakim. All these kings because their kingship
was contested. שהיה גדול ממנו שתי שנים, shehayah gadol mimenu shetei shanim,
Yehoyakim was two years older. ואותו שמן ve’oto shemen and all that,
now back to our major point, at least the point of this.
That oil that was used all those times, וכולו קיים לעתיד לבוא,
vechulo kayam le’atid lavo, will be around for the future. שנאמר שמן
משחת קודש יהיה זה לי לדורותיכם. shene’emar shemen mishchat kodesh yihyeh zeh
li ledoroteichem. זה בגימטריא שנים עשר zeh begimatria shenem asar was 12
log. הוה. havah. Okay, let's read just a little bit more. אמר
מר. amar mar. ואפילו כהן גדול בן כהן גדול טעון משיחה. ve’afilu
kohen gadol ben kohen gadol ta’un meshichah. Kohen Gadol the son of
a Kohen Gadol needs to be anointing, as we saw from our
Mishnah, anointing a Kohen Gadol is significant in terms of
the status at least for the special Korban of the par. מנלן?
menalan? דכתיב, dechtiv, והכהן המשיח תחתיו מבניו. vehakohen hamashiach tachtav mibanav. Okay.
Who is anointed from the son? So even though it's from the
sons, you still anoint him.
נימא קרא והכהן מתחתיו מבניו, neima kra vehakohen mitachtav mibanav, why didn't
it just say the one who serves, you know, from the sons?
מאי המשיח? mai hamashiach? קא
משמע
לן דמבניו דכהן גדול אי הוי משיח הוי כהן גדול ואי לא
לא הוי כהן גדול.
ka mashma lan demibanav dekohen gadol i havei mashiach havei kohen gadol
ve’i lo lo havei kohen gadol. That no, the Kohen Gadol status,
it doesn't mean he's not a Kohen Gadol, but because there's also
the principle of מרובה בבגדים merubeh bivgadim like we saw in our
Mishnah, but it means that a certain status of the Kohen Gadol
comes through the act of anointing. And even though it's clear who
the next Kohen Gadol would be and it's the son of the
current Kohen Gadol, we're also going to see that the Kohen Gadol
as opposed to the kingship was not the same concept of a
ירושה. yerushah. So that's partly why you needed the שמן המשחה shemen
hamishchah because it wasn't assumed that it just went from father to
son the same way kingship was presumed to go from father to
son. So part of what the משיחה meshichah does is it indicates
who
the next Kohen Gadol is. But part of it, but you could
also do that through in the, you know, in through the wearing
of the special clothes. Part of it is like the Torah makes
it clear when it discusses the מילואים. miluim. Part of it is
it's a special act
of sanctification, of dedicating the Kohen Gadol to the service, okay, and
it gives
him this status of the par. So there's two reasons why you
do the משיחה. meshichah. משיחה meshichah is something that fundamentally is done
to the כלי המשכן klei hamishkan of which the Kohen Gadol was
part of and it's a special sanctification, and that's less relevant to
a king. And also Kohen Gadol not necessarily father to son, so
you need it more to designate. Okay. מאי המשיח קא משמע לן
דמבניו דכהן גדול הוי משיח הוי כהן גדול ואי לא לא הוי
כהן גדול. mai hamashiach ka mashma lan demibanav dekohen gadol havei mashiach
havei kohen gadol ve’i lo lo havei kohen gadol. אמר מר. Okay,
so I guess we'll end with there for now and then we
will continue tomorrow with the idea of the king. But one of
the things to note with the king is the contrast that the
kingship is presumed to be a ירושה yerushah and goes down father
to son, and that's why there's less of a need for or
you generally don't use the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishchah. כהן, kohen, we
assume like whoever is the, maybe there's a slight preference to the
son of the current כהן גדול, kohen gadol, but there's generally also
an assumption of the one who is the most worthy. It's not
seen as much of a ירושה. yerusha. So for those two reasons
you use the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha for the כהן גדול. kohen
gadol. It's not automatically a ירושה, yerusha, so it's needed to designate
and also as part of sanctifying the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, sanctifying
those things that are associated with the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, which
is less relevant when dealing with kings. Okay, we'll end here.